So today's דף daf is דף ג daf Gimmel and we continue
with the very bottom of ב עמוד ב. Beis amud Beis. So
far we have two explanations for the משנה, mishna, the debate of
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. The easiest explanation
was רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman's that בית שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't hold
of מוקצה muktzah or נולד nolad and בית הלל Beis Hillel does.
The גמרא Gemara rejected it for a seemingly
very minor textual reason, very questionable reason, but anyway, it allowed it
to move on to the next explanation which is רבה, Rabbah, which
introduces this issue of הכנה, hachana, preparing, that is based on a
verse. So according to this an idea of הכנה hachana that's not
מוקצה muktzah and rabbinic based but based on a verse, and that
is specifically, as רש"י Rashi points out, around preparing for the סעודה
seudah of שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. And therefore there's
a problem of something that was completed not on a weekday that
you are going to want to do for your סעודה seudah of
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom Tov, even if it's completed naturally,
the egg being completed in the inside of the chicken for a
שבת Shabbos that precedes יום טוב, Yom Tov, that is a problem
because it wasn't prepared on a weekday and ready already on a
weekday for the meal on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Maybe that's specifically
around eating, not so clear. So now we continue to a third
reason and it picks us up here at the bottom of ב
עמוד ב. Beis amud Beis. So let's take a look. רב יוסף
אמר, Rav Yosef amar, two lines from the bottom of ב עמוד
ב. Beis amud Beis. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says: גזירה משום פירות
הנושרים. gzeirah mishum peiros hanoshrin. Here's the reason why. It's a rabbinic
problem, not a מוקצה muktzah problem. It's a rabbinic problem of fruit
that drop off of a tree. You can't eat fruit that drop
off of a tree, even in situations it might not be מוקצה.
muktzah. Why would it not be מוקצה? muktzah? We can talk about
it in a minute. But you cannot eat fruit that drop off
of a tree, even if it's not a מוקצה muktzah problem, because
you might come to then pick it off the tree. So he
says an egg that drops from a chicken is like fruit that
drops off of a tree. And therefore, even again, remember one of
the questions is what type of a chicken are we talking about?
Even a chicken that was set aside to be eaten so there's
no מוקצה muktzah problem, no נולד nolad problem, it's like food that
fell off from food. Okay? But food that fell off from food
is not always allowed. A fruit that falls off of a tree
is not allowed because you might come to pick the fruit, and
the same thing applies to the egg. So the גמרא Gemara says
yes, but
how are
you going to come to pick the egg? So that's what אביי
Abaye asks. אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. So אביי Abaye says
to him: פירות הנושרים, peiros hanoshrin, fruit that falls off of a
tree, טעמא מאי, taama mai, what's the reason that that's a problem?
גזירה שמא יעלה ויתלוש. gzeirah shema yaaleh veyitosh. We're afraid you'll go
up in the tree and start pulling fruit off of it. So
היא גופא גזירה ואנן ניקו ונגזור גזירה לגזירה? hi gufa gzeirah veanan
neikum venigzor gzeirah legzeirah? It itself is a safeguard. Don't do this
lest you come to pick the fruit off the tree. And we're
going to make a safeguard to a safeguard? Meaning, right, the safeguard
is like a fence around a fence. The fence is supposed to
protect the actual transgression. So why are you going to make a
fence to protect the fence? You don't, right, that's something that's sort
of exceeding your
need and right to be protecting and legislating to protect תורה Torah
law, to make a fence around a fence. One fence is enough.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, כולא חדא גזירה היא. kula chada
gzeirah hee. It's all one גזירה. gzeirah. Now what does it mean
it's all one גזירה? gzeirah? Sometimes you could sort of understand that
to be like some things we want to make a fence around
a fence. תוספות Tosafot actually says this in a number of places.
Think about what we don't do in terms of meat and milk
together. Not only do we not eat meat of an animal of
mammals, we also don't eat chicken meat which obviously is not biblically
prohibited, they don't have mother's milk. Not only do we not cook
them together, we don't even eat them cold together. Not only do
we not even eat them cold together, we wait six hours between
them. So תוספות Tosafot says in that discussion of meat and milk,
there are many times we do make a גזירה לגזירה. gzeirah legzeirah.
Like for whatever reason, the rabbis just decided they wanted to have
a lot of safeguards. But that's not exactly the answer of כולא
חדא גזירה היא. kula chada gzeirah hee. כולא חדא גזירה היא kula
chada gzeirah hee is saying fundamentally it's not a fence around a
fence, it's all part of the first fence. Which means, as רש"י
Rashi explains, it's not like the rabbis said: Let's not allow fruit
around a
tree... that is the fence. Oh, you know what? Let's not allow
eggs because that'll lead to fruit that fell off of a tree.
No, they didn't say that. They said: What's included in the category
of fruit that falls off of a tree? You know what, conceptually
if we abstract it, that category should include any type of food
that sort of falls off of its originator source on שבת. Shabbos.
So that would also include the egg. So the egg is not
prohibited because it'll lead to the fruit apple on the ground. The
egg is prohibited because when the rabbis said don't eat fruit that
fell off a tree, they made it an abstract category and they
included everything that was like that. And therefore the egg was part
of that original גזירה gzeirah because the original גזירה gzeirah was more
abstract and included all cases of food that fell off of its
originating source. So that is the explanation. It is a type of
fruit that falls off a tree. It's not a גזירה gezeirah to
lead to that case, it's a type of fruit that falls off
of a tree. And even though in its particular case you're not
afraid that you'll do a violation, that's part of the rabbinic edict.
So that's his explanation of the reason of the egg, that בית
הלל Beit Hillel has this concern and בית שמאי Beit Shammai does
not. Now the גמרא, Gemara, now
תוספות Tosafot by the way wants to know, okay, that's all very
nice, but as I said, why is it not מוקצה, muktzah, right?
Why would it not be מוקצה? muktzah? And תוספות Tosafot says well,
maybe we're talking about a scenario, right, if you couldn't pick the
fruit off the tree on שבת Shabbat or יום טוב, Yom Tov,
it's just מוקצה muktzah because it's off limits. Why do you need
a special prohibition not to eat it once it fell off? It
was already מוקצה. muktzah. So תוספות Tosafot says well, maybe we're talking
about, you know, that there are like ravens in the area and
the ravens would normally, you know, eat from the fruit anyway. Okay,
but like you don't have access to it. Well, maybe they would
normally eat from the fruit when it would drop and the fruit
was ready to drop. And he sort of says maybe we can
construct the scenario where, you know, even though it's attached to the
tree you're expecting it to drop by itself and it wouldn't be
considered like out of reach. You know and that's interesting because it
gets to the question well maybe you're expecting the egg to be
laid by itself. But somehow because this is visible and it's on
the tree and it's hanging by a thread and it's about to
drop, maybe that it would not be מוקצה. muktzah. But nevertheless it's
going to be prohibited because of this concern. Okay, so that's an
interesting question why you need this explanation if it's already, you know,
if it why doesn't מוקצה muktzah sort of cover you? All right,
now the גמרא Gemara continues and the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אמר
ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי, Abaye, I'm sorry, so that
was what that was רב יוסף's Rav Yosef explanation. רב יצחק אמר,
Rav Yitzchak amar, three lines from the top, גזירה משום משקין שזבו.
gezeirah mishum mashkin shezavu. It's a concern of liquids that flow, which
means you're not allowed to squeeze lemons or grapes on שבת Shabbat
and יום טוב. Yom Tov. And if you can't squeeze them, you
also let's say you just had a pile of grapes sitting around
and then by themselves some liquid flowed out. You cannot drink the
liquid that flowed out by itself because if we let you drink
the liquid you'll come to squeeze the grapes. Okay, so it's the
same idea. This is a thing that flowed out by itself. The
egg flowed out of the chicken by itself. Don't eat the egg
because you'll come to squeeze the chicken. Okay, so it's going to
be the same issue. But the point is it fits in this
category of something that fell and derived from something else that was
not allowed. So we put the egg in the same category. So
not the fruit from the tree but the juice that came off
of the grapes. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye
said to him, משקין שזבו, mashkin shezavu, liquids that flow, so טעמא
מאי, taama mai, why is that forbidden? גזירה שמא יסחוט, gezeirah shema
yisochot, we're afraid you'll squeeze the actual grapes themselves if we let
you drink the juice that flowed out of it. היא גופא גזירה
ואנן ניקום ונגזור גזירה לגזירה? hi gufa gezeirah va-anan nekum ve-nigzor gezeirah
le-gezeirah? That itself is a safeguard and we're going to make a
safeguard to a safeguard? גמרא Gemara says כולה חדא גזירה היא. kula
chada gezeirah hi. It's not, don't have the egg you'll come to
drink the
grape juice. It's when we said don't have things that flowed out
of their originating source, we spoke about it in a more abstract
term that included that with an egg that came out of a
chicken. Okay, so those are our explanations. So two about מוקצה, muktzah,
one about this new idea הכנה דרבנן, hachanah de-rabbanan, which is all
about a יום טוב Yom Tov שבת Shabbat issue when they come
back-to-back and about preparing for the meals, a hard idea to get
our heads around. And these two last explanations which say forget about
מוקצה, muktzah, it's not מוקצה muktzah because presumably it's a chicken that's
set aside for eating, so it's not a מוקצה muktzah issue, there's
that question what's the nature of the chicken. And it is but
it is a problem because it falls into these rabbinic categories of
fruit off of a tree or liquids that come from fruit. Let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says now, sort of stops for a
moment and assesses where we're at. So let's take a look. The
גמרא Gemara says like this: כולהו כרב נחמן לא אמרי, kuleihu ke-Rav
Nachman lo amri, all the other אמוראים Amoraim didn't say רב נחמן's
Rav Nachman explanation which seems to be the simplest that it's a
debate about מוקצה muktzah and it's about a chicken set aside for
laying eggs, כי קשיא ki kashya because of our question that then
it should have not just debated the egg, it should have debated
the chicken as well. כרבה נמי לא אמרי, ke-Rabbah nami lo amri,
they don't say like רבה, Rabbah, this idea of biblical idea of
preparing for the meal of שבת Shabbat or having the stuff prepared
by itself. הכנה לית להו, hachanah leit lehu, they don't hold of
this new idea called הכנה. hachanah. מוקצה muktzah and a rabbinic issue
they hold of but they don't hold of this idea that like
the food has to be naturally prepared from beforehand and so on,
that's רבה's Rabbah idea. אלא, Ela, but let's deal with the last
two categories which is in this it's a chicken that's set aside
for eating, it's not a מוקצה muktzah problem and the question about
which of these types of rabbinic issues, the fruit of the tree
or the juice that came out of the grapes. אלא רב יוסף
מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב יצחק? ela Rav Yosef mai taama lo
amar ke-Rav Yitzchak? רב יוסף Rav Yosef who said it's similar to
fruit off a tree, why doesn't he say like רב יצחק, Rav
Yitzchak, it's similar to juice that comes out of a grape? אמר
לך, amar lach, so he'll say to you, ביצה אוכלא, beitzah ochla,
because
look an egg is food. An egg is food, it's not a
liquid. And פירות אוכלא, peiros ochla, so the more comparable case of
something that fell off of something else is fruit, fruit is food
and an egg is food. And they're both round, although he didn't
say that. But they're both food, okay? לאפוקי משקים דלאו אוכלא, lafukei
mashkim d'lav ochla,
it's less similar to the case of liquid that flows from a
grape, liquid isn't food, it's a liquid. So physically it's more similar
to the food to the fruit category and that's how come it
was I think put into that category. רב יצחק מאי טעמא לא
אמר כרב יוסף? Rav Yitzchak mai ta'ama lo amar k'Rav Yosef? So
why did רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak prefer to categorize it in the
juices that came off of that flowed from the grape rather than
the fruit that fell from the tree? How about the fact that
that's a liquid and that's a solid? So אמר לך amar lach
he'll tell you look, I acknowledge that difference, but here's what makes
a bigger difference to me. ביצה בלועה, beitza blu'ah, an egg is
absorbed swallowed up you know it's inside the chicken. So the thing
that was held inside of something came out of the thing that
it was held into. That's like the juice that's in a grape
that comes out of the grape. Okay, ביצה בלועה לאפוקי פירות דמיגלו
וקיימו, beitza blu'ah lafukei peiros d'miglo v'kaimu, it's less it's not similar
to fruit which is exposed and present in front of you. Okay
so that is the reason why and there so it's one of
these two questions, which is it more similar to? Again this points
to the fact that it's not a גזירה לגזירה. gezeira l'gezeira. It's
not don't do this lest you do that. It's a fact that
conceptually it's similar. If we just abstract the idea of fruit a
little bit or the idea of liquids that flow a little bit
we'll be able to include the egg case. So it's somewhat similar
in an abstract category and the question is which category is it
more similar to? Is it more like the fruit that fell from
the tree or more like the liquids that ran off of the
grapes? So you had a question.
I'm just surprised they don't say that the egg is a liquid.
Egg is a liquid.
Oh why should they? It's not. Okay so what?
An egg is as much of a liquid as a grape?
Oh you mean because inside of it it's a liquid. Yeah alright,
again that gets to the fact that that's not visible to us
so why should it be a problem? Anyway, so that is now
here's an interesting question. All of this that you'll pick the fruit
off of the tree or that you will you know squeeze the
fruit is understood to be a problem even on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, right? Because we're saying that this is a גזירה gezeira that
applies on שבת ויום טוב Shabbos v'Yom Tov and the egg falls
into this case. So תוספות Tosafos asks a question. I don't get
it. If you can do things for the sake of food, right,
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can שחט shacht an animal, you
can cook etc. why can't you pick fruit off of a tree?
Okay, now that's a real important question that we're going to get
back to particularly in the third פרק perek which deals with what
are the things that are allowed, how far does that allowance go
on יום טוב? Yom Tov? But I want to just read you
the question. If you take a look at this big תוספות Tosafos
גזירה, Gezeira, the middle-sized line. Let me describe where it is.
He says, where is it? I'm I am trying to tell you
if I won't be stopping interrupted so he says,
so he says like this. He said, אך תימה, ach teima, the
line starts with the word יבלענו yivla'enu about exactly in the middle
of the middle of the middle-sized line. First word is
יבלענו. yivla'enu. Do people see that? Yes. Yes. Alright טוב, tov, I'm
just kidding. No, but okay. אך תימה ach teima
he says it's a wonder. מה שמא יעלה ויתלוש, mai shema ya'aleh
v'yislosh,
why do we have to be concerned you'll go up and pluck
it off the tree? הא אפילו לכתחילה מותר לתלוש, ha afilu l'chatchila
mutar litlosh, shouldn't it be allowed even לכתחילה? l'chatchila? דאוכל נפש מותר,
d'ochel nefesh mutar, you can do things for the sake of food
on יום טוב Yom Tov and don't tell me you could have
done it ahead of time. Doesn't matter you could have done it
ahead of time, you're allowed to cook on יום טוב Yom Tov
even though you could have cooked ahead of time. So why aren't
you allowed to pick something off of a tree? So he says
so he goes through a whole discussion and then he says at
the end,
two lines down in the wide lines he says like this, על
כן פירש רבינו נתנאל, al kein peireish Rabbeinu Nesanel,
you see that? מקינון? mikinon? People have that? Right in the beginning
of the second widest line like four words in. Okay, yeah. Therefore
רבינו נתנאל Rabbeinu Nesanel explains בירושלמי b'Yerushalmi
that here's the explanation given in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Yeah, here's what
it says. אך אשר יאכל לכל נפש ach asher ye'achel l'chol nefesh
וסמיך ליה, v'samich lei, you can do whatever you need to for
eating, ושמרתם את המצות. ushmartem es hamatzos. Okay and you should observe
the מצות. matzos. So what?
Okay go ahead.
Okay אותם מלאכות osam melachos משמור ואילך, mishimur v'eilach, the מלאכות melachos
that apply from the time when you have to watch the מצה.
matza. When do you have to watch the מצה matza and prevent
it from becoming חמץ? chametz? When water first hits flour. When does
water hit flour? At the stage of kneading. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
says the juxtaposition here is telling you when do we when is
it allowed to do things for food? At the same type period
of preparation when if you're making מצות matzos you have to worry
about it becoming חמץ. chametz. Okay so it's very timely, starting at
the moment of kneading onwards, משמור ואילך, mishimur v'eilach, הם מותרות דהיינו
מלישה ואילך, hem mutaros d'hainu milisha v'eilach, from kneading onwards. אבל שאר
מלאכות דמקודם לכן אסורין. aval sh'ar melachos d'mikodem lachen asurin. anything that
is earlier is forbidden. Okay, so this becomes a very important conceptual
principle about מלאכה melacha for food being permissible on יום טוב Yom
Tov that it does not mean I can go out into my
field and start with my scythe, you know, taking, cutting down the
wheat. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi puts a limit to it, something and the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi thinks it's a biblical limit and learns it from this
connection to מצה Matzah and basically says only from the period of
preparation that is kneading onwards, from when it's closer to being complete.
Conceptually, what that's about is an interesting question. You could just say,
well, you know, it's later in the stage of development and not
earlier in the stage. But what exactly is that distinction? And some
אחרונים, Acharonim, I think want to conceptualize it in an important way.
They say the types of preparation that gets done in the home,
not the type of preparation that takes place out in the fields,
is processed before it gets to the, you know, before it gets
to you. That you can do the type of preparation... Now, of
course, it's funny, like we would think, okay, so שחיטה shechting is
certainly not the preparation that could be done in the home. But
that's in our homes, right? In their, right, in their homes, you
know, no, you go to your backyard and you שוחט shecht your
chicken. So the type of preparation that's the preparing the food that
you do in your home context, that's okay. But the harvesting, the
grinding, the sifting, all of that is done out in the field,
it's done at a large scale, not on a small scale in
the home, and that's different. That's a nice conceptual explanation of why
this is the period that it's allowed. But this is a very
important question about how broad is the Torah's allowance of doing things
that are allowed for food. And because this גמרא Gemara specifically makes
it clear you can't pluck fruit off of a tree and you
can't squeeze fruit on יום טוב, Yom Tov, well, why the heck
not? Isn't it food-related? We get this idea, you know, he brings
in this ירושלמי Yerushalmi of only from the period of לישה lishah
onwards, of kneading onwards. Now, I do want to say, by the
way, that it's not so simple. First of all, not everybody thinks
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is the basis, not everybody thinks that the distinction
is דאורייתא, de'oraisa, and there's also, we'll see later, discussions of things
you could do earlier in the process that's more allowed on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So I don't know if people are aware, but
certain spices you're allowed to grind on יום טוב, Yom Tov, like
spices that would not be as sharp and as pungent beforehand. So
you can in theory, I mean we'll talk about it, don't anybody
פוסק pasken this way until we discuss it later, but, you know,
take your pepper mill, you know, fresh pepper with that? Right? Which
you could never do on שבת Shabbos but you could do, possibly
do on יום טוב, Yom Tov, we'll discuss. Now, grinding is much
before לישה. lishah. Grinding is the turning of the wheat into the
flour. It's much before the kneading. So it's not so clear that
this is the absolute cutoff, but what it's introducing is not everything
is allowed for the sake of food, there are some cutoffs. Yes.
Grinding of flour used to be done in homes. We never hear
of that today, but it used to be done a lot in
homes.
They didn't have mills? I mean, they didn't do it at large
scale?
They had mills and well, large-scale mills were fairly early in history,
but in many societies, people had hand...
Okay, so again, what I gave was an explanation for the distinction,
right? In the end, the way it's quoted in הלכה halacha is
מלישה ואילך. milishah va'eilach. That's like the phrase. Those are two, so
again, it's interesting that it ties back to פסח, Pesach, and those
are just two words. You want to show everybody how knowledgeable you
are about יום טוב? Yom Tov? So says, oh yeah, it's מלישה
ואילך, milishah va'eilach, right? So just those two words, לישה lishah onwards,
that's when it's allowed. Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. So ואף רבי יוחנן v'af Rabbi
Yochanan says the גמרא, Gemara, where are we? Oh, ואף רבי יוחנן,
v'af Rabbi Yochanan, even רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so line starts with
word רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. סבר גזירה משום משקין
שזבו. Savar gezeirah mishum mashkin shezavu. He holds that the reason of
the משנה, mishnah, of the egg, is because it's in the category
of liquids that flow, and that's forbidden. רבי יוחנן רמי רבי יהודה
אדרבי יהודה ומשני. Rabbi Yochanan rami Rabbi Yehuda a-Rabbi Yehuda u-mishani. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had a problem, what seemed to be a contradiction
of two statements of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and he gave an
answer. But we're going to focus on the fact that he had
the problem to begin with belies a certain assumption of what this
is all based on. תנן. Tnan. We have the following משנה mishnah
in שבת. Shabbat. אין סוחטין את הפירות להוציא מהן משקין. Ein sochtin
es haperos lehotzi mehen mashkin. You cannot squeeze fruit to extract the
liquid. ואם יצאו מעצמן אסורין. V'im yatzu me'atzman asurin.
And here's the concern about the juices that flow on their own.
It's exactly in the משנה. mishnah. The juice that flowed on its
own from the fruit, even if you didn't squeeze it, is forbidden.
רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says there's
a distinction. אם לאוכלין, Im l'ochlin,
if the fruit was set aside to be eaten, not to be
juiced, like, you know, let's talk about like, I don't know, you
have your grapefruit, you're going to eat it. היוצא מהן מותר. Hayotzei
mehen mutar. So if some juice comes out of the grapefruit, you
can you can eat it. Okay, you know, when you're eating a
grapefruit, you can eat some of the juice. ואם למשקין, V'im l'mashkin,
however, if the fruit was set aside for liquid, like you had
a pile of grapes you were going to turn into grape juice
and eventually into wine, היוצא מהן אסור. Hayotzei mehen asur. What comes
out is forbidden. What's the logic? The logic is the whole reason
it's forbidden is you might accidentally come to squeeze it. Well, if
we let you drink the grape juice, you'll come to squeeze grapes,
because fundamentally you're interested in the juice. But if we let you
drink a little of the runoff liquid of the of the grapefruit,
we're
not afraid. So he says whether we allow you to drink the
liquid that runs off by itself is a function of whether the
fruit is basically there for eating, or whether it's there for being
turned into liquid. One second. So now that's the first statement of
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So. Now, עלמא alma you see, כל אוכלין
לרבי יהודה אוכלא דאפרשי. kol ochlin l'Rabbi Yehuda ochla de'afreshei.
Any food that comes from food, something set aside to be eaten,
not to be made into a juice, but something like the grapefruit
set aside to be eaten, fruit the something that comes from it
is just considered food that separated and is permissible. Okay, so the
juice of a grapefruit since the grapefruit is about being eaten, that's
okay. רמיני, Ramini, now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said but I have
a problem, I'm going to show a contradiction. ועוד אמר רבי יהודה,
Ve'od amar Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the following. This
is a debate in עירובין Eiruvin about two days of ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah. Are they considered one continuous קדושה, kedusha, a two-day קדושה,
kedusha, or is it each day is independent, is it like a
normal case of a two-day יום טוב Yom Tov of ספקא דיומא?
sefeika deyoma? As if I don't know if today is יום טוב
Yom Tov but I don't know if tomorrow is יום טוב. Yom
Tov. What's the difference? The difference is the following debate. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says even ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is like a normal
two-day יום טוב. Yom Tov. And here's the implication. מתנה אדם על
כלכלת פירות, Matne adam al kalkalat peirot, a person can stipulate about
a basket of fruit, ביום טוב ראשון, beyomtov rishon, on the first
day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, ואוכלה בשני, ve'ochla besheini, and eat
it on the second day. What does that mean? Which means here
I've got my basket of fruit, okay, it's a basket, and I
forgot to take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros from it. It's טבל. tevel.
It's אסור. assur. And I'm not allowed to take תרומות ומעשרות trumos
u'maasros on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But here's what I'm going to
do. I'm going to take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros and I'm going
to say here's the deal. Okay, if today is really יום טוב,
Yom Tov, then forget about this. I'm not doing anything. Okay, if
today is a weekday, because it's a two-day יום טוב Yom Tov
each day is you don't know, weekday or יום טוב, Yom Tov,
that's sort of the fiction in which we live with the two-day
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So if today is יום טוב Yom Tov
I didn't do anything. If today is a weekday I'm taking תרומות
ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. All right, then I come to tomorrow. I can't
eat it today because today might be a יום טוב Yom Tov
and I didn't do anything. Then I come to tomorrow and I
say okay, I'm doing it again. If today is יום טוב Yom
Tov and yesterday was a weekday, then I'm now now not doing
anything, but yesterday I already fixed the problem, because yesterday was a
weekday and today is יום טוב. Yom Tov. And if today is
a weekday and yesterday was the יום טוב, Yom Tov, so then
now I'm taking the תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. So now by the
fact they did that stipulation on both days, I can eat it
today. That's what you get by a normal two-day יום טוב Yom
Tov when you do you view each day is independent and we
pretend each day you don't know if it's if it's יום טוב
Yom Tov or if it's a weekday. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says you can do the same thing on on two days ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. It's not considered one indivisible unit of two days,
each day is like a normal two-day יום טוב Yom Tov and
you can say I don't know if today's יום טוב, Yom Tov,
I don't know if tomorrow's יום טוב Yom Tov and allow you
to do that trick. That's one trick you can do. וכן, Vechein,
similarly, ביצה שנולדה בראשון תאכל בשני. beitza shenolda berishon tochel besheini.
Okay,
if an egg was born on today, first day יום טוב, Yom
Tov, I can't eat it today because today might be יום טוב,
Yom Tov, but I can eat it tomorrow. Why can I eat
it tomorrow? Well, because tomorrow I'll tell you look, make up your
mind. If you think today is יום טוב, Yom Tov, then yesterday
when it was born was a weekday, so I can eat it
today. Okay, if they tell me no no, but maybe today is
חול chol and it was born yesterday on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
good, it was born on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but today is
a weekday, so it's not מוקצה. muktzah. Okay, so if it's a
two-dayer, right, if it was born on the first day יום טוב,
Yom Tov, I can eat it on the second day. That's what
he says and the Rabbis disagree and they say ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah is different, they say on a normal יום טוב Yom Tov
we would agree with you, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is different, it's
a continuous two-dayer and therefore you cannot pray if today, if tomorrow,
it's all one day יום טוב. Yom Tov. Fine. That's a debate
of a two-dayer or one-dayer. But what the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
is saying is you see that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda agrees that
there's a problem with an egg laid on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Like the first day it's still a problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says עלמא, alma, where's the גמרא? Gemara? ומשום, ve'mishum,
so you see, בשני אין בראשון לא, besheini in berishon lo,
you can only eat it on the second day, not the first.
So the whole point of bringing in that question of two-dayer or
one-dayer was to show that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda agrees with בית
הלל Beis Hillel and there's a problem with the egg laid on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now, why is that a problem? So he
says look, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says I don't get it. On
the one hand רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds of the problem of
the egg. On the other hand, what did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
say about the juice that ran off from the grapefruit? Good or
not good?
Good! Because the grapefruit was there to be eaten, not to be
squeezed. So he says so then why is so רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says so why is the egg any different? The egg comes
from a chicken that set aside to be eaten, not a chicken
set aside for laying eggs, which in that case it's sort of
like the grapes ready to be squeezed. But no, it's set aside
for a chicken that's ready to be eaten, it's like the grapefruit.
So if the juice of the grapefruit is okay, why is the
egg from the chicken set aside to be eaten okay? So that's
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan question. But before we get to the answer,
you know this is great about the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא's Gemara
you know let's unpack what's the assumptions underlying your question. The fact
that you said I've got a problem because this case of the
egg doesn't parallel רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position about the juice of
the grapefruit, so you're assuming that the whole idea behind the egg
is because it's in this category of juices that run off of
fruit. I could give you four other reasons about the egg. the
egg. It's a מוקצה muktzeh *muktzah* issue, it's fruit from the tree,
it's רבה Rabbah, *Rabba*, but the fact that you're bothered by these
two רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda*s shows you're assuming the egg
case is based on the fruit that comes the juices that come
from the fruit and it bothers you that they don't fit together.
So that's the fact that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that shows
you that רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan* sides with the position that the
egg case is based on the problem of juices that come from
fruit. So now we're going to look at what his answer is,
but now we're just sort of lining up that this is another
backing to this position that it's in this category of juices that
come from fruit. Charlie, you had a question.
Oh, regarding fruits that are designated for juice versus designated for eating,
is that this particular apple or grapefruit or orange, or is it
the whole type, all apples, all oranges, because at times oranges have
been eaten.
Right, it's a very good question and it's it generally goes by
the type of fruit, not by the particular one in front of
you or your intention. Of course if there are different strands or
varieties of oranges as opposed to different oranges then that's different, but
that still has to do with the whole brand. It's also it's
also relates to other issues that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* isn't directly
or not exactly on the table right now, which is not just
are we afraid you'll lead to squeezing but when is squeezing fruit
a biblical violation? It might only be a biblical violation by grapes
and olives where the juices were the were like seen as like
you know more
important than the actual fruit itself. The whole purpose of the fruit
was to get to the juices as opposed to other types of
things. So there's other factors that relate to it, but the basic
issue is the the simple answer to you is it goes by
the type of fruit, not by your particular intention, although again it
could be more nuanced than that, but that's certainly the thrust. Okay,
but there are different types of fruit within the same, you know
like I said, strands of oranges. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this, so now we have רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan*'s problem.
We got that רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan* sees the egg as a
type of juices that come from the food and now he says,
so why does it why does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda*
bother? Shouldn't it be like the juice that comes from the grapefruit?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומשני *umeshani*, so what's now let's
get to רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan*'s answer, ומשני רבי יוחנן *umeshani Rebbe
Yochanan*, and רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan*'s answer is מוחלפת השיטה *muchlefet hashita*,
that okay let's reverse the position. Okay, which is always like okay
that wasn't such an interesting answer. Yeah, we got a problem, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda* doesn't fit, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe
Yehuda* allows the juice from the grapefruit and doesn't allow the egg.
So you know what I'm going to do? I'm going to reverse
the position, that it's really the רבנן *Rabbanan* that allow the juice
from the grapefruit and it's רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* that says all
juices are a problem. So if all juices are a problem, it
would include the egg case. All right? So before we had it
that the רבנן *Rabbanan* said all juices, רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* said
no, the juice from a grapefruit is okay. In order to make
it work with the egg, which is like the fruit from the
grape juice, we're having רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* say all juices are
no good and it's the רבנן *Rabbanan* who say, makes a difference
between things that's for food and things that are for squeezing. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* just, that's his answer, okay, not such
a thrilling answer, that's his answer, but now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
points out what I've been saying about the underlying assumption of the
question. ומדקא מירמי להו אהדדי *umidka mirmi lehu ahadadi*, from the very
fact that רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan* throws these two things together, is
bothered by what he perceives as a contradiction between these two positions
of רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*, שמע מינה חד טעמא הוא *shema mina
chad taama hu*. You see he thinks that it's all part of
the same reason. You see he thinks that it's based on the
issue of that the egg problem is based on the issue of
liquids that come off of the fruit. Okay, so that's the immediate
issue for us, that רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan* thinks the egg is
based on the liquids that come from the fruit. Now we're going
to give different answers to רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan*'s question. If we
concede that that is the issue of the egg, is there another
way to explain the fact that רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* isn't being
consistent with the grapefruit case and with the egg case, rather than
just sort of reversing which one רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* said. So
let's take a look at other answers to that question. רבינא Ravina
אמר *Ravina amar*, רבינא *Ravina* says לעולם לא תיפוך *le'olam lo teipoch*,
going back to this question of רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan*, you don't
have to reverse רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*. רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* could
say the juice of a grapefruit is okay and the egg is
still and the egg is still a problem. Well, but how does
that work? דרבי יהודה לדבריהם דרבנן קאמר *deRebbe Yehuda lidvreihem deRabbanan ka'amar*,
because what רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* isn't really saying the egg is
a problem. The same way the juice from the grapefruit is okay,
the egg would be okay. So why does he talk about the
egg that was born on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* and
two days of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*? He's just saying
to the רבנן *Rabbanan*, based on your position, לכו קאמר להו *lechu
ka'amar lehu*, לדידי *lididi*, as far as I'm concerned, אפילו בראשון נמי
שריא *afilu berishon nami sharya*, I would allow an egg on the
first day ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah* because I don't believe
that the egg there's a problem with the egg. דאוכלא דאפרסי הוא
*de'uchla de'aparsei hu*, it's just food that came from food, it's like
the juice of a grapefruit. So personally I don't hold of בית
הלל Beit Hillel *Beit Hillel*, I don't believe that the egg is
a problem. אלא לדידכו *ela ledidchu*, but you who believe that the
egg is a problem for whatever reason, אודי לי מיהא *odi li
miha*, you should at least concede to me דבשני שריא *debashani sharya*
that on the second day of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah? *Rosh Hashanah*
it should be allowed because of this idea of ספיקא דיומא *sfeika
deyoma*, which is really saying a way of saying like the egg
was just a convenient case of exploring this question of is it
two separate קדושות kedushot, *kedushot* or one? Like one on the first
day will be allowed on the second. But it's really not showing
that he's committed to the idea that there's a problem with the
egg. He could be using it as a convenient way of articulating
his position that two days of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah are two
separate days. So according to you guys that you've got a problem
with an egg, here should be you should allow it on the
second day of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah Remember, this is all about
ראש השנה. Normal יום טוב Yom Tov, everybody would agree to this,
that if it's born on the first day you can have it
on the second. Question is how do you look at two days
ראש השנה? Okay? ואמרו ליה רבנן Ve-amru lei rabanan and the rabbis
say back to him: No, no, קדושה אחת היא. kedusha achata hi.
No, not two קדושות, kedushot one קדושה. kedusha. So we think it
remains forbidden on the second day. So that's an easier answer than
reversing his position. He's saying even though he discusses the egg, he
doesn't really think the egg is forbidden even the first day but
he's discussing it because it demonstrates this question of is it two
separate קדושות or one long קדושה? kedusha? Okay, so that's another answer
to that question. And now one final answer. רבינא בריה דרב עולא
אמר, Ravina brei de-Rav Ulla amar, רבינא the son of רב עולא
Rav Ulla says: הכא בתרנגולת העומדת לגדל ביצים. hacha betarnegolet hamedet legadel
beitzim. Nah, why you sweat yourself a קאפ? kop? This issue about
the egg born on the first day of ראש השנה is not-
you don't have to put it, even if the normal problem of
the egg is because it's like liquids that drained off of a
fruit, that's the way you understand the normal problem of the egg.
Remember, there's always two scenarios: was the chicken there to be eaten
or was the chicken there to lay eggs? We've been assuming the
chicken is there to be eaten and therefore we and then we
should say the egg should be okay and we have to search
for a new reason to make the egg forbidden and we say
it's like liquid that comes from a fruit. But maybe רבי יהודה
in his discussion of ראש השנה was talking about a chicken that
was there for laying eggs and it's a simple מוקצה muktzeh, problem.
Okay? So he says: הכא בתרנגולת העומדת לגדל ביצים. hacha betarnegolet hamedet
legadel beitzim. We're talking about a chicken that's there to lay eggs.
רבי יהודה לטעמיה דאית ליה מוקצה, Rabbi Yehuda litaimei d'it lei muktzeh,
and רבי יהודה holds of מוקצה, muktzeh, like we know רבי יהודה
holds of מוקצה, muktzeh and argues with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who
doesn't hold so much of מוקצה muktzeh. but רבי יהודה holds of
מוקצה. muktzeh So even if we concede that the problem with the
egg is a type of a juices that ran off, okay, that's
when we have to look for a new reason when it's an
egg coming from a chicken that's to be eaten. But if the
chicken is there to lay eggs, then everybody agrees it's a problem,
that's a מוקצה muktzeh issue. Alright, so what have we said right
now? We've said that we have four explanations for why בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai debate the egg case. One
is that it's a real מוקצה muktzeh issue and the chicken is
there to lay eggs and it's a real מוקצה muktzeh issue and
בית הלל and בית שמאי Beit Shammai are debating whether they hold
of מוקצה muktzeh or not. The other three explanations all assume they
look, if it was there to lay eggs, everybody would agree it's
a problem. Then it's מוקצה muktzeh and even בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
no debate. That would be a complete consensus. So what's the debate?
The debate is when it's there to be eaten where there's not
a good reason why the egg should be a problem if the
chicken was there to be eaten. It should just be like food
that came from food. And then you have three explanations why there
would be a problem. One of רבה, Rabbah this idea of הכנה
hachana and that the things you're going to have for the meal
have to be finished the day before and so on. And then
the two explanations the גמרא Gemara is focusing on on this new
rabbinic category of juices from food or fruit that fell off of
a tree. Okay but all of that, which the גמרא Gemara at
the end has reminded us, is when the chicken is there to
be eaten and you need to come up with a new reason
why there should be a problem. But if the chicken is there
to lay eggs, everybody- there's no debate according to this, even בית
שמאי Beit Shammai would agree that's a מוקצה muktzeh issue. Alright, so
everybody good? Those are our four explanations of the משנה. Mishnah. Now
the גמרא's Gemara going to introduce a ברייתא Baraita to continue to
explore these different explanations. Yes.
Is it accurate that מוקצה muktzeh and רבה's Rabbah idea of הכנה
hachana are similar to each other?
Okay, so let's wait till we get to מוקצה muktzeh, and until
we more explore הכנה. hachana. I know, but that's why I've been
repeating that רבה's Rabba idea of מערב me-erev specifically is about סעודת
שבת, seudat Shabbat, סעודת יום טוב, seudat Yom Tov, focuses on eating.
So the basic answer is let's assume no. Okay, but we will
continue to revisit that. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי.
Meitivei. Now I'm going to bring a ברייתא, Baraita, says the גמרא,
Gemara and see if we can challenge some of the different explanations
about the egg issue.
And see how this ברייתא Baraita plays out given the different explanations.
אחד ביצה שנולדה בשבת ואחד ביצה שנולדה ביום טוב, Echad beitza shenolada
beShabbat ve-echad beitza shenolada beYom Tov, whether the egg was laid on
שבת Shabbat or the egg was laid on יום טוב, Yom Tov
אין מטלטלין אותה. ein metaletlin otah. You cannot move it, means it's
מוקצה, muktzeh, basically. ולא לכסות בה את הכלי, Velo le-chasot bah et
hakli, not to use it to cover a vessel. I don't know,
you got like, you know, the top of your- remember those old
fashioned milk bottles? So you don't have the top so you just
stick an egg in it. Okay, it would work, it would keep
a pretty tight thing. Problem is getting taking it off would it
break the egg. But alright. You can't use it to close up
a bottle top. To close up a bottle. ולא לסמוך בה כרעי
המטה, Velo lismoch bah karei hamita, not to support the legs of
a bed. I have no idea what that means, like how is
it supposed
to support the leg of an egg without cracking? I just don't
understand what's going on there. Okay, somebody will explain it to me.
All over the ש"ס. Shas.
Okay fine, I don't know. Okay anyway, alright, moving on. Anyway, it's
מוקצה, muktzeh. you can't use it even- Even if you've got a
legitimate need, אבל כופה עליה את הכלי בשביל שלא תשבר. Aval kofeh
aleha et hakeli bishvil shelo tishaver. What you can do, and this
is becoming a very convenient type of a prop, you can put
a vessel on top of it. Now why should you not be
able to? Because the egg is מוקצה. muktzeh Here's a question: can
you move something מוקצה muktzeh for something not מוקצה muktzeh? to protect
something that is מוקצה? muktzeh. And that's a question of the one
that says you can't, the phrase is אין כלי ניטל אלא לצורך
דבר הניטל. Ein kli nital ela litzorech davar hanital. A כלי, kli,
a vessel, cannot be moved except for the sake of something else
that is allowed to be moved, which is a complicated way of
saying you can't move a vessel to protect for the sake of
מוקצה. muktzeh But this ברייתא braita holds otherwise.
This ברייתא braita holds, no, actually you can, so while you can't
move the egg, you can cover it up with something to prevent
it from being broken. Okay, so that's point number two.
Okay, וספיקא אסורה. Usfeika asura. Now here's a new idea. If there's
a doubt, presumably a doubt whether the egg was laid on יום
טוב Yom Tov, or whether it was laid before יום טוב, Yom
Tov then it still remains forbidden. Even if you might say ספיקא
דרבנן, sfeika d'rabbanan, we'll look at that. But if there's a doubt,
it remains forbidden. ואם נתערבה באלף כולן אסורות. Ve'im nitarva b'elef kullan
assurot. This egg that was laid on יום טוב Yom Tov, got
mixed up with a thousand eggs that were laid from beforehand. You
can't eat any of them. Now, on יום טוב, Yom Tov after
יום טוב Yom Tov you can eat it. But on יום טוב
Yom Tov you can't use any of your eggs. Now why normal
ביטול bitul doesn't apply, we'll get to, right? It should be בטל
בששים batel b'shishim at least and so on. We'll discuss all of
that. Okay, so now we're going to analyze this ברייתא braita and
see how it plays out.
בשלמא לרבה דאמר משום הכנה, Bishlama leRabba de'amar mishum hachana, רבה Rabba
who says that the whole problem is this idea of preparation and
he sees that from a verse that it's biblical, so good, we
understand why if there's a doubt it remains forbidden. הוי ספיקא דאורייתא,
Havei sfeika d'oraita, because רבה Rabba's found it, made it a real
biblical issue. So it's a doubt about a biblical matter whether the
egg was laid today or yesterday. וכל ספיקא דאורייתא לחומרא, Vechol sfeika
d'oraita lechumra, and all biblical doubts we're going to be strict about.
Now by the way I should point out that we here have
assumed that רבה's Rabba's position would lead to it also being מוקצה
muktzah and not able to be moved, not just not able to
be eaten. Because the whole beginning of this ברייתא braita spoke about
not moving it. And is that really biblical or is that a
rabbinic extension of the biblical idea? But at least what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is, and remember by the way רבה's Rabba only
problem of it really being a problem was when יום טוב Yom
Tov. and שבת Shabbos were juxtaposed and here presumably we're talking about
a regular יום טוב. Yom Tov. But at least what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is that according to רבה Rabba there's a biblical
idea in there somewhere. Okay, it starts from this biblical concept and
therefore it's not crazy that we say in a place of doubt
we're going to be strict. But all the other opinions fundamentally were
completely rabbinic issues from scratch, right? You know, rabbinic invented problems. It's
not something that has a fundamental דאורייתא de'oraita base. So why should
we be strict in a case of doubt? That's just the question.
גמרא Gemara says, אלא לרב יוסף ולרבי יצחק דאמרי משום גזירה, Ela
leRav Yosef uleRabbi Yitzchak de'amri mishum gezeirah, but רב יוסף Rav Yosef
and רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak that say either it's because of the
juices or because of the fruit from the tree, it's all a
rabbinic issue. So ספיקא דרבנן היא, sfeika d'rabbanan hi, it's a rabbinic
doubt. וכל ספיקא דרבנן לקולא, Vechol sfeika d'rabbanan lekula, we should be
lenient. So why does it say if you have a doubt about
the egg, be strict? גמרא Gemara says, אמר לך, Amar lach, you
can say, סיפא אתאן לספק טריפה, seifa atan lesafek treifa, let's just
take out that parenthesis,
סיפא אתאן לספק טריפה. Seifa atan lesafek treifa. When it says a
doubt is forbidden, we're no longer talking about the egg laid on
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov, Basically, it did this shift.
It says if an egg laid שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom
Tov don't move it. Parenthesis, while we're talking about eggs, let's talk
about if you have a doubt whether an egg was laid from
an animal that was a טריפה treifa or not. Okay, so an
egg was laid by a chicken and if the chicken itself was
a טריפה, treifa, so then the egg also is טריפה treifa like
the chicken. So if you have a doubt about whether the egg
came from a
טריפה, treifa, don't eat the egg, because that's a דאורייתא de'oraita doubt.
Now of course, how can you switch from an egg laid on
יום טוב Yom Tov. to an egg from an animal that might
be a טריפה treifa without telling—I get that you might want to
talk about the two side by side because they're both issues about
eggs. But how could you switch without telling you're talking about a
different case? Okay, so it's a very forced read but in order
to deal with this issue of why would a doubt be forbidden,
it deals with this case of you don't know if it came
from an animal that's a טריפה treifa or the animal is a
doubtful טריפה. treifa. By the way, I should say an interesting application
of this issue that things that come from animals that are טריפה
treifa is no good is every few years people raise this question
about why can we drink milk because apparently a lot of dairy
cows might be טריפה treifa and especially if you shoot them up
with hormones and that might cause holes in whatever. So how can
we drink milk if it all comes from ספק טריפה safek treifa
or whatever? So I'll let you worry about that, sit on that
question. You can research it, there's plenty of stuff on the web
that discusses it. Charlie, you have a question.
Yeah, I was going to ask about not being בטל batel with
a thousand. Even תרומה trumah is more.
Okay, so we'll see about that. Like I said, don't worry, we're
getting to it.
So one other point before we go on. So the גמרא Gemara,
has explored how this ברייתא braita works according to רבה Rabbah that
says it's based on הכנה, hachana, and according to רב נחמן Rav
Nachman and רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, or רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef that say it's based on like the fruit
of the tree or the juices from the fruit. The one opinion
the גמרא Gemara had ignored was רב נחמן Rav Nachman who says
that the issue is about a straight מוקצה muktzah question, right? רב
נחמן Rav Nachman who said we're talking about a chicken that's there
to lay eggs and it's a straight מוקצה muktzah question. The גמרא
Gemara. seems to have really pushed רב נחמן Rav Nachman completely aside.
Like it's the simplest explanation of the משנה. Mishnah. The simplest explanation
of what's the issue with the egg is is it מוקצה muktzah?
or not מוקצה? muktzah Do we have a מוקצה muktzah problem or
not a מוקצה problem? גמרא's Gemara completely ignored רב נחמן Rav Nachman
and it's dealing now with רבה and this הכנה hachanah idea or
with this issue about fruit of the tree or juices from the
tree, גזירה gezeirah idea. Okay, so now we have this answer, this
weak answer that we've shifted gears and we're talking about eggs that
from an animal that might be a
טריפה. treifa. סיפא אתיא לספק טריפה. Seifa atya lesafek treifa. So the
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, i hachi, if that's the case, אימא
סיפא, eima seifa, look at the very end. The very end says
נתערבה באלף כולן אסורות. nisarva be'elef kulan asurot. Now we're getting to
this part of it. If it gets mixed up in a thousand,
they all remain they're all forbidden. There's no ביטול, bittul, you can't
use any of the eggs on יום טוב. Yom Tov So the
גמרא Gemara says אי אמרת בשלמא ספק יום טוב ספק חול, iy
amart bishlama safek Yom Tov safek chol, if it's like the simple
sense of the ברייתא, Baraita, you don't know if the egg was
born on the weekday or was it born when יום טוב Yom
Tov. began. So I understand why it's not בטיל battil in a
thousand. Why? Because here's your answer Charlie, הוי דבר שיש לו מתירין,
havei davar sheyeish lo matirin, because it is a matter that will
make become permissible. The egg will be permissible tomorrow, when it's חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. It's only forbidden today on יום טוב. Yom Tov
So I will understand why I won't let you eat the eggs
and won't allow ביטול, bittul, because if something will become permissible later,
we're not going to allow ביטול bittul to work now. וכל דבר
שיש לו מתירין, vekhol davar sheyeish lo matirin, anything that has something
that will make it permissible, אפילו באלף לא בטיל, afilu be'elef lo
battil, isn't בטיל battil even in a thousand. So this is a
very important principle in the גמרא, Gemara and the logic of it,
what's the logic? The way רש"י Rashi explains the logic is look,
if we apply ביטול, bittul, then you're going to be eating something
that right now is not kosher. Now it's true, halakhically it is
kosher because ביטול bittul took a place and it made it into
something that's מותר. muttar. But the reality is you're still going to
be it's a workaround, you found a way to eat something you
shouldn't be eating. We're not saying you did it deviously, but that's
just the reality that it was a workaround and you're actually eating
something that normally is off limits. So normally we understand, okay, that's
what ביטול bittul says, because otherwise you'd have to throw it all
out. But if all we have to do is ask you to
wait a day, so better to wait a day. Wait a day,
don't rely on this idea of ביטול, bittul, better to wait. Okay,
the phrase that רש"י Rashi uses sometimes is עד שתאכלנו באיסור תאכלנו
בהיתר. ad shetokhlenu be'issur tokhlenu beheter. You know, rather than eating something,
you know, eating it while it's forbidden, you know, again, it would
be permissible because of ביטול, bittul, but fundamentally you're eating something that
you shouldn't be eating, wait to eat it at a time when
it's all permissible. Don't rely don't use ביטול bittul if you don't
have to. This by the way is very relevant for פסח, Pesach,
which is coming up. And as you know, by פסח Pesach it's
like things, you know, even a tiny speck is a problem. Right?
Where does that come from? So according to some, I mean it's
a whole question about a particular גמרא Gemara and גירסאות girsos in
the גמרא. Gemara But anyway according to some it's an application of
this idea of דבר שיש לו מתירין. davar sheyeish lo matirin. That,
you know, because after פסח Pesach it won't be a problem anymore.
So therefore we can't allow, you know, ביטול bittul to work. כל
דבר שיש לו מתירין אפילו באלף לא בטיל. kol davar sheyeish lo
matirin afilu be'elef lo battil. There are questions about to what degree,
when, you know, when you apply that category and so on. But
anyway, that's what the גמרא's saying. If this egg was a problem
of some type of a particular problem on יום טוב because of
the juices or the fruit from the tree or whatever, then I
could say fine, I'm not going to allow ביטול bittul to work,
you'll just wait till tomorrow. But if it's a question of a
טריפה, treifa, then I should allow ביטול bittul to work, then it's
a normal non-kosher thing, let it be בטיל battil in sixty at
least. Why should it not be בטיל? battil? So let's see what
the גמרא says. So the גמרא says,
אלא אי אמרת, ela iy amart, if you say, ספק טריפה, safek
treifa, that this is a brand new case at the end, about
a possible possibly coming from a טריפה treifa chicken, so דבר שאין
לו מתירין היא, davar she'ein lo matirin hi, it's something that there's
no way to be permissible on this egg because of the טריפה
treifa concern, ותיבטל ברובא, vetibattel beruba, let it just become בטיל. battil.
And he says even a simple majority make it בטיל. battil. Now
that's funny, why didn't you need sixty? Okay, so this is actually
a principle that if you have things that are not commixed. If
they're commixed it could lead to have taste. But they're separate units,
what's called יבש ביבש. yavash beyavash. Each thing is an independent unit,
and then and it's all the same, they're all eggs. So really
actually a simple majority is enough, you don't even need sixty. Okay,
so it's all eggs, they're separate units, there's no commixture. In that
case the הלכה halakhah is a simple majority is enough. But whether
you say majority, whether you say sixty, why should at least let
there be let ביטול bittul work? Right? Why should it not be
בטיל battil even in a thousand? So let's see what the גמרא
says. Okay, אלא אי אמרת, ela iy amart, let's see it again,
סיפא ספק טריפה, seifa safek treifa, דבר שאין לו מתירין היא, davar
she'ein lo matirin hi,
it's something that there's no way to be permissible on this egg
because of the טריפה treifa concern, ותיבטל ברובא, vetibattel beruba, let it
just become בטיל. battil. וכי תימא ביצה חשובה ולא בטלה, vekhi teima
beitzah chashuva velo battela, ah, I have a new reason why, because
an egg is significant and it's not בטיל battil because It is
like a separate, its own unit, and it doesn't become part of
a conglomerate. Like you ever, you know those, they have this great
poster, right, about with these penguins, like, you know, like sadly now
or whatever, we're losing the ice floes and the penguins. But anyway,
you know, like thousand penguins on this, like, you know, on this
ice floe, whatever it is, and then one penguin is sort of
dancing and saying, I just got to be me. You know? So,
but the point is, like, so you have things, like you have,
if you have like a lot of things together, can the idea
of ביטול bitul apply? If you look at them as like a
conglomerate and a collective and nothing is, things aren't their own thing,
then okay, it loses its identity in the mass of everything else
and ביטול bitul applies. But things that every time you look at
it, it's like its own unit, right? It's discrete unit. Now, that
doesn't just mean physically discrete because that would, but it means that
they're significant to the object. You would not, you know, make it
part of a conglomerate. You would, you know, you would always look
at it independently. Like, let's say a car. Okay? So, you would
never say, oh yeah, you know, I've got like I've got a
bundle of cars here, right? Every car always deserves its own attention.
So, therefore, then it's never בטל batel because it's never part of
the conglomerate. It always, each item is standing by itself. So, maybe
we should say that by eggs. Now, what makes an egg important?
So, here becomes a question and the phrase the גמרא is going
to look at is דבר שבמנין, davar she-be-minyan, things that are sold
by number and not by, right, not by weight or not by
volume. They're never made sort of, is that the right word, conglomerated
with other things. So, for example, like you know how the checkout
aisles it says ten items, now it says twelve, twelve items or
less? Which, so the point is it's grammatically wrong because it should
be twelve items or fewer. Right? This is the difference. Right? If
you say fewer is when you have numbers, units, each one is
counted. Less and more is when you have something that's a conglomerate
of things like, you know, water, less or more water. So, the
גמרא says this is the idea of דבר שבמנין. davar she-be-minyan. If
it's a type of a thing that is counted, then that means
that it's never made part of a mixture and of a conglomerate.
It's always how many, it's each one is always distinct. Okay? And
therefore ביטול bitul won't apply. So, if you always sell eggs by
the number of eggs, then you're always counting each one individually. Now,
of course, you could say, really? I mean, a dozen, yes, means
twelve, but the whole idea is like sort of bundle it all
together. So, we'll take a look at, we'll see about that. Yeah.
I thought you said separate units only mean the majority? What? I
thought you said separate units only mean the majority. Yes, but what's
the distinction?
The separate units of things that are conglomerated. So, if you have,
let's say, let's say, you know, you don't buy, you don't count
the number of potatoes. You always buy potatoes by weight or you
buy it by like a bag, a bushel of potatoes or whatever
it is. So, those are, they have separate units, but they're a
types of things that are always looked at in terms of the
collective. Right? As opposed to something that is separate and always looked
at distinctly. This is דבר שבמנין. davar she-be-minyan. So which category does
the egg fall into? So, that's the question, is which category does
the egg fall in? Okay, so that's going to be the argument
why it's not בטל. batel. So, let's take a look. So, it
says like this. So, הניחא, hani-cha, if you say the egg is
important and not בטל, batel, הניחא, hani-cha, that's good למאן דאמר le-man
de-amar כל שדרכו למנות שנינו. kol she-darko limnot shaninu.
Anything that is sometimes counted, there's a question of a text in
a משנה, Mishna, what things are not בטל. batel. We'll see the
משנה Mishna in a minute. And does the משנה Mishna say anything
that is sometimes counted, anything that can be counted? So, eggs sometimes
are sold by number and therefore the number, each one is independent
and not בטל. batel. אלא למאן דאמר ella le-man de-amar את שדרכו
למנות שנינו. et she-darko limnot shaninu.
If your גרסא, girsa, if your text in the משנה Mishna is
things that only are counted, not that sometimes are counted, but only
are counted. So, cars you never sell by volume or weight. Okay?
You only sell by unit. But a lot of other things, like
eggs, you could sell a basket of eggs. You could conglomerate eggs.
Okay? It's not only counted. So, if your idea is things that
are only counted, so מאי איכא למימר, mai ika le-meimar, you don't
have a good explanation. Because the egg should be בטל batel because
sometimes it's counted but often it's not and therefore it should be
בטל. batel. Now, where is this debate whether only counted or sometimes
counted? דתנן, de-tnan, because we taught in a משנה Mishna the following.
מי שהיו לו חבילי תלתן, mi she-hayu lo chavilei tiltan, somebody had
bundles of, I don't know what's תלתן, tiltan, fenugreek? Clovers. Clovers, sorry
about that. Somebody had, what? Fenugreek. Ah, there we go. Anyway, who
knows. Somebody has bundles, I like the word fenugreek, it's a funnier
word. Anyway, whoever has bundles of fenugreek.
So, של כלאי הכרם, shel kilei ha-kerem, and they were stuff that
was grown together with grapes. So, they're כלאים. kilayim. ידלקו, yidliku, you
have to burn them. That's what you do with stuff that's כלאים
kilayim together with grapes.
נתערבו באחרות, nit'arvu be-acherot, if that got mixed up with other bundles
of fenugreek, ואחרות באחרות, ve-acherot be-acherot, and something from the first mixture
fell into a second mixture. כולן ידלקו *Kulan yidlaku* and all have
to get burned, דברי רבי מאיר *divrei Rabbi Meir*. So meaning ביטול
*bitul* doesn't apply here, everything is אסור *assur*. וחכמים אומרים *V'Chachamim omrim*
means the חכמים *Chachamim* say, no, יעלו באחד ומאתיים *ya'alu b'echad u'matayim*.
200 is enough to cause ביטול *bitul*. ביטול *bitul* does work. Five
things that are very sort of weighty, like כלאים *kil'ayim* and טבל
*tevel* and תרומה *trumah*, sometimes you need 100 or 200, a simple
60 is not enough. Okay, so the חכמים *Chachamim* say, no, this
is the normal הלכה *halacha* of כלאים *kil'ayim*, 200 is enough to
create ביטול *bitul*. Okay, that's the normal הלכה *halacha* of כלאים *kil'ayim*.
But they say ביטול *bitul*'s possible. But רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says
no, no ביטול *bitul*. Why is רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* saying no
ביטול *bitul*? Let's take a look. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר *She'haya Rabbi
Meir omer*, because רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* used to say, את שדרכו
למנות *et she'darko limnot*, something that is only, that is counted, that's
always counted. Per- meant bundles of fenugreek were always counted by number,
never by weight or volume. So מקדש *mekadesh*, sanctifies what it's mixed
up into. Sanctifies not a good way, forbids everything it gets mixed
up into. It means no ביטול *bitul* on something which is את
שדרכו למנות *et she'darko limnot*, which is fundamentally a unit that is
counted. וחכמים אומרים *V'Chachamim omrim* and the חכמים *Chachamim* say, אינו מקדש
אלא שישה דברים בלבד *eino mekadesh ela shisha devarim bilvad*. Only six
things, again, that funny word, that sanctify, six things that make their
mixture forbidden. Six things that are not בטל *batel* because they're so
important. רבי עקיבא אומר שבעה *Rabbi Akiva omer shiva*, and רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva* says seven. ואלו הן *V'elu hen* and these are they:
אגוזי פרך *egozei Phrach*, nuts that come from a place called Phrach.
וקלחי כרוב *V'kilchei chruv*... I'm sorry, I skipped a line. ורמוני בדן
*V'rimonei Badan* and pomegranates that come from a place called Badan. וחביות
סתומות *V'chaviyot stumot*, sealed barrels of wine presumably. וחלופי תרדין *V'chalifei tardin*
and bundles of beets, I believe that's תרדין *tardin*. It's spinach. Spinach,
I'm sorry, spinach. וקלחי
כרוב *V'kilchei chruv* and bundles of cabbage. ודלעת יוונית *V'dilaat yevanit* and
a Greek gourd. רבי עקיבא מוסיף אף ככרות בעל הבית *Rabbi Akiva
mosif af kik'rot ba'al ha'bayit* and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* adds home-baked
bread. So these things are... you can't make a general rule, things
that are counted are never בטל *batel*. You can't say abstractly. There
are particular things that are very important that we always focus on
as independent units and those things aren't בטל *batel*. Now of course,
really? Like this for life, for all eternity it'll be these six
or seven things? So רמב"ם *Rambam* says okay, you know, the idea
is every location, every time period you have to identify what are
those things that are important that aren't בטל *batel*, but it's not
an abstract general rule of things that are counted. You have to
make your list and identify and know context and you know and
sort of all matters in terms of you know how they're perceived
by society. Fine. But let's focus on רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* makes a general rule: things that are counted. So
the question is what is the phrase, what is the rule? And
here's the debate. Okay,
so let's just see one more line. הראוי לערלה ערלה הראוי לכלאי
הכרם כלאי הכרם *Haroyeh l'orla orla, haroyeh l'kil'ay hakerem kil'ay hakerem*. Some
of these things could be a problem of ערלה *orla* because they
grow from trees, other of these things could be a problem of
כלאים *kil'ayim*, they don't grow from trees but they could be planted
together with vines, with grapes. Anyway, דאתמר עלה *de'itmar alah*, it was
said regarding this משנה *Mishnah*: רבי יוחנן אמר את שדרכו למנות שנינו
*Rabbi Yochanan amar et she'darko limnot shaninu*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* is
forbidding only things that are את שדרכו *et she'darko*, like they're only
counted. ריש לקיש אמר כל שדרכו למנות שנינו *Reish Lakish amar kol
she'darko limnot shaninu*. No, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* is forbidding if they
are anytime counted, everything that might be counted, not only things that
are only counted, but anything that might be counted. Meaning, so ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish* is saying according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, even
if this thing is sometimes sold by weight, by volume, by the
bushel, by the basket, since sometimes it's counted, that's enough to give
it importance and it's not בטל *batel*. So back to this question:
why is this egg which is only a rabbinic problem that's mixed
up with a
thousand... why is this egg that's mixed up with a thousand eggs
not בטל *batel*? If it's a rabbinic problem of יום טוב *Yom
Tov*, we understand that the principle of דבר שיש לו מתירין *davar
she'yesh lo matirin*, just wait till tomorrow. But you're trying to say
that this egg at the end is talking about a possible טריפה
*treifa* to explain why a doubt should be a problem, then why
should it be a problem when it's mixed up with a thousand
eggs? Just let normal ביטול *bitul* work. It's a normal forbidden object,
let ביטול *bitul* work. And the answer is well, according to ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish*, anything that's sometimes counted isn't בטל *batel*. That's his
understanding of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*: כל שדרכו למנות *kol she'darko limnot*.
That would explain the egg. Now that's very nice, but רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*'s version of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* is את שדרכו למנות
*et she'darko limnot*, things that are only counted. And the egg is
not only counted, so we're back to our question of why there
wouldn't be ביטול *bitul*. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says: הניחא לריש
לקיש *Ha nicha l'Reish Lakish*. So according to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*,
I get why there's no ביטול *bitul* if it's a טריפה *treifa*
because the egg is sometimes counted. אלא לרבי יוחנן מאי איכא למימר
*Ela l'Rabbi Yochanan mai ika l'meimar*? According to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*,
why isn't there ביטול *bitul*? The egg might sometimes be counted but
it's not only counted, ביטול *bitul* should apply. So we're going to
continue with this tomorrow, why there is no ביטול *bitul* if you've
turned the case of the egg into a case of a טריפה
*treifa* issue. But again, if the egg is just a יום טוב
*Yom Tov* problem, it's a simple explanation that there's no ביטול *bitul*
because just wait till tomorrow and you can eat it tomorrow. Okay.